A Guide to the Krasimira Choneva Architectural Papers, 1958-1997
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Krasimira Choneva Architectural Papers
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2007-003
3.1 cu. ft.; 1 map case; 1 box
The Krasimira Choneva Architectural Papers include conceptual and working drawings as well as supporting documents for six projects. The projects range in date from 1958-1997 and were all designed and completed in Bulgaria by Krasimina Choneva. The collection also includes one biographical sketch written by Choneva herself as well as an additional biography written by Milka Bliznakov in 2007.
Krasimira Choneva
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Krasimira Choneva Architectural Papers were donated to Special Collections in 2007. The collection was obtained in two accessions both in 2007.
Biographical Information
Krasimira Zheliazkova Choneva was born on September 23, 1935 in Varna, Bulgaria. Her father, Zheliaazko Maldjiev (b.1901) was an insurance agent and her mother Elena Ivanova Maldjieva (b.1898) was a middle school teacher who moved with her family to Varna from Macedonia after the Llinden uprising in 1903.
Choneva's family emphasized hard work and education, as a result Choneva's brothers attained university diplomas in electronics and technology and her cousins studied architecture. At the encouragement of her family Choneva enrolled in a Construction and Technological High School where she began her study of architecture. In addition to academia, Krasimira participated in sports, specifically swimming, eventually taking second place at a national competition in Bulgaria.
"This sport helped me to aim at being the best, to follow the prescribed rules and to organize my time and activities. I didn't continue my architectural education in the university for the following reasons," Krasmira states, "First, because I was in training to reach the international standards in swimming. Second, university entrance in the architecture program required contacts within the ruling communist party."
Choneva's professional architectural experience began in 1958 when she started working in the construction office of Varna's ship building industrial complex. The experience cemented her "love and commitment for architecture." In 1959, Choneva's won a draftsman competition in the design organization for the town of Varna.
Choneva worked for this state organization until her mandatory retirement in 1990, calling this period her "university training." The work experience provided Choneva with the opportunity to work with several architects including, Marin Marinov; Simeon Dimitrov; Kosio Khristov; Julia Angelova; Daniel Ognianov; and Philio Ginev on multiple design projects.
In 1961 Choneva married Marin Choveve (b.1932) a conductor of the leading Bulgarian choir "Morski Zvutzu" (The Sounds of the Sea). The choir performed abroad giving her the opportunity to visit multiple countries and familiarize herself with their architecture. "During the years of the 'Iron Curtain' such knowledge gave me considerable advantage," Choneva recalls.
In 1971 Choneva became involved with construction of mass-housing utilizing prefabricated panels. The system developed after WWII in Western Europe and was later imported by the Soviet Union. "Regardless of the persistent endless criticism of prefabricated multi-family apartment housing," Krasmiria insists, "it was justified by the large migration of people from the agricultural sector (small towns and villages) to cities with large industrial developments. The prefabricated system gave to almost all urban dwellers the option to reside in their own apartment with adequate space and sanitary facilities. The modular panels (5.10 meters x 3.60 meters) allowed for functional arrangement of the required spaces. Speedy construction, however, allowed for sloppy finishes and shoddy appearance of the apartment buildings. I am glad to have responded to the societies demand for improved quality and to my personal desire to give the ugly panels a more attractive façade appearance."
In the latter part of the 1980's the Union of Bulgarian Architects (SAB) invited Choneva to join their organization. This was a distinct honor giving Choneva the right to open a private practice after the change in Bulgarian government between 1989 and 1990. Choneva opened a private office where she designed residential houses and apartment buildings for twelve years from 1990-2002.
Choneva had three children, two daughters and one son. Her daughter, Liuliana Marinova Chonevea (b. Oct. 14, 1962) joined her at the practice when she graduated Sofia Polytechnic in 1990. Upon her retirement Choneva transferred the practice to her daughter. Her son Kalin Tchonev (b.1971), also a choral conductor and piano performer, resides in North Carolina.
Scope and Content
The Krasimira Choneva Architectural Papers span the year's 1958 to 1997 and cover projects Choneva completed in Bulgaria. The collection includes conceptual drawings, working drawings and supporting documents for six projects including, Hotel "Victor" in St. Nikola; Apartment building for B. Mikhov on Llinden St. in Varna; Pavilion with changing rooms to the Euxinograd Palace near Varna; Vacation house for Burov in the subdivision of Briz, Varna; Vacation house for Manasiev in Euxinograd near Varna; and a Vacation house for Shulekov on the Monastikski Rd. area. The collection also includes one biographical sketch written by Choneva herself, as well as an additional biography written by Milka Bliznakov in 2007.
The majority of Choneva's work includes architectural drawings of residential apartment buildings and vacation homes. Items of particular distinction in the collection include Choneva's early work on the Pavilion for Euxinograd Palace and her apartment designs utilizing prefabricated panels and accent colors.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically according to project.
Contents List
- 14 Photographs. Photos of unidentified apartment buildings with prefabricated panel housing and colorful elements. (Box-folder 1:1)
- 7 Photographs; 1 black and white image, exterior elevations for multi-family housing; 2 photos, apartment building in Varna, Bulgaria; 1 photo, single family home near Varna; 3 photos, sports pavilion at Euxinograd Palace,1958. (Box-folder 1:2)
- 11 handwritten slides of biography written in Bulgarian by Krasimira Choneva. (Box-folder 1:3)
- Papers 1-5; Conceptual Drawings, Pavilion with Changing Rooms, 1958 (Drawer 32: Drawer 10: Folder 1)
- Papers 6-14; Working Drawings, Vacation House for Manasiev in Euxinograd near Varna, Bulgaria, 1991 (Drawer 32: Drawer 10: Folder 1)
- Papers 15-23; Conceptual Drawings, Hotel "Victor" in St. Nikola near Varna, Bulgaria, 1991 (Drawer 32: Drawer 10: Folder 2)
- Papers 24-35; Working Drawings, Hotel "Victor" in St. Nikola near Varna, Bulgaria, 1992 (Drawer 32: Drawer 10: Folder 3)
- Papers 36-47; Conceptual Drawings, Apartment Building for B. Mikhov on "Ilinden" Street in Varna, Bulgaria, 1993 (Drawer 32: Drawer 10: Folder 4)
- Papers 48-62; Working Drawings, Apartment Building for B. Mikhov on "Ilinden" Street in Varna, Bulgaria, 1993 (Drawer 32: Drawer 10: Folder 5)
- Papers 63-75; Working Drawings, Vacation House for Burov in subdivision of Briz in Varna, Bulgaria, 1994 (Drawer 32: Drawer 10: Folder 6)
- Paper 76; Site Plan, Vacation House for Shulevov in "Monastikski" Road area, 1994 (Drawer 32: Drawer 10: Folder 7)
- Papers 77-83; Conceptual Working Drawings, Vacation House for Shulevov in "Monastikski" Road area, 1994 (Drawer 32: Drawer 10: Folder 7)